勇敢的心
苏格兰
公元1280年
我要讲述的是威廉·华莱士的故事
I shall tell you of William Wallace.
英格兰的历史学家会说我是个骗子
Historians from England will say I am a liar,
但历史正是由那些绞杀了英雄的人书写的
but history is written by those who have hanged heroes.
苏格兰国王去世时没有留下儿子
The king of Scotland had died without a son,
当时的英格兰国王
and the king of England,
残忍的异教徒  长腿爱德华
a cruel pagan known as Edward the Longshanks,
宣称自己是苏格兰国王
claimed the throne of Scotland for himseIf.
苏格兰贵族们奋起反抗
Scotland's nobles fought him
但又为王位互相残杀
and fought each other over the crown.
长腿邀请贵族们进行和谈
So Longshanks invited them to talks of truce,
不带武器  只带一名男侍
no weapons, one page only.
当地有个农民叫马尔科姆·华莱士
Among the farmers of that shire was Malcolm Wallace,
他是拥有自己土地的平民
a commoner with his own lands.
他有两个儿子  约翰和威廉
He had two sons, John and William.
我让你待在家的
I told you to stay.
我的活儿干完了
Well, I finished my work.
我们要去哪儿
Where are we going?
马克安得鲁家
MacAndrews'.
他本该在谈判后来找我们的
He was supposed to visit when the gathering was over.
我能一起去吗
Can I come?
不行  回家去  孩子
No. Go home, boy.
但我想去
But I want to go.
回家去  威廉  否则你就要挨打了
Go home, William, or you'll feel the back of my hand.
回家去  威廉
Go you home, William.
马克安得鲁
MacAndrews!
上帝啊
Holy Jesus.
-没事的  -威廉  威廉
- It's all right! - William! William!
威廉  威廉  没事的
William! William, it's all right.
没事的  别怕  孩子
It's all right. Easy, lad.
威廉
William.
要我说我们立刻反击
And I say we hit back now!
我们不能反抗他们  那是去送死
We cannot fight them! It's suicide!
得做些什么
Something's got to be done.
华莱士说得对  我们要反抗
Wallace is right! We fight them!
所有想要反抗的贵族都在那个会议上
Every nobleman who had a will to fight was at that meeting.
我们打不赢军队
We cannot beat an army.
只靠五十个农民没戏
Not with 50 farmers.
我们不用打赢  只是要反抗
We do not have to beat them, just fight them.
谁支持我
Now, who's with me?
我支持你  华莱士
I am, Wallace.
好吧  好吧
All right, all right.
就这么定了
Ready.
你这是想去哪儿
Where do you think you're going?
我要跟你一起
I'm going with you.
你要跟我一起吗
You're going with me, are you?
-那你打算做些什么  -我会帮忙
- And what are you going to do? - I'm gonna help.
你一定是个好帮手
And a good help you'd be, too,
但我需要你呆在这
but I need you to stay here
在我不在时照顾好这里
and look after the place for me while I'm away.
我可以打仗
I can fight.
我知道  我知道你能打仗
I know. I know you can fight.
但智慧才会让我们成为男子汉
But it's our wits that make us men.
明天见
See you tomorrow.
-英格兰人  -趴下
- English. - Get down.
你父亲和哥哥都走了
With your father and brother gone,
他们会杀了我们再烧了农田
they'll kill us and burn the farm.
靠我们了  哈米什
It's up to us, Hamish.
爸
Da?
威廉
William.
过来  孩子
Come here, lad.
出自《诗篇》130篇
耶和华啊  我从深处向你求告
De profundis clamavi ad te, Domine.
主啊  求你听我的声音
Domine, exaudi vocem meam.
愿你侧耳
Fiant aures tuae intendentes
听我恳求的声音
in covem deprecationis meae.
耶和华啊  请给予他们永远的安息
Requiem aeternam dona eis, Domine.
愿圣光永远照耀他们
Et lux perpetua luceat eis.
请安息吧
Requiescat in pace.
阿门
Amen.
-阿门  -阿门
- Amen. - Amen.
威廉
William.
我是你的叔叔  阿盖尔
I'm your uncle. Argyle.
你长得和你母亲很像
You have the look of your mother.
今晚我们住这里
We'll stay here tonight.
明天你跟我回家
Tomorrow you'll come home with me.
我不想离开
I don't want to leave.
你也不希望你父亲死去  对吗
You didn't want your father to die either, did you?
但这就是事实
But it happened.
神父不是做了祷告了吗
Did the priest give a poetic benediction?
"愿耶和华赐福给你  保护你"
"The Lord bless thee and keep thee".
是用拉丁语说的吗
It was in Latin?
你不懂拉丁语吗
You don't speak Latin?
那我们以后得补上这一课  对吧
Well, that's something we shall have to remedy, isn't it?
愿耶和华赐福给你  保护你
The Lord bless thee and keep thee.
愿耶和华的光芒照耀你
The Lord cause his light to shine on thee.
愿耶和华向你仰起脸
The Lord lift up his countenance upon thee
赐你平安
and give thee peace.
阿门
Amen.
你的心是自由的
Your heart is free.
勇敢地去跟随吧
Have the courage to follow it.
他们在做什么
What are they doing?
用他们自己的方式告别
Saying goodbye in their own way.
亡命的风笛演奏着亡命的旋律
Playing outlawed tunes on outlawed pipes.
我们的父亲去世时
It was the same for me and your daddy
我和你父亲也看到了同样的仪式
when our father was killed.
首先  学会用这里
First, learn to use this.
之后我会教你怎么用这个
Then I'll teach you to use this.
很多年后
Many years later,
长腿爱德华  英格兰国王
Edward the Longshanks, King of England,
包办了他长子的婚礼
supervised the wedding of his eldest son,
他的长子将继承他的皇位
who would succeed him to the throne.
阿门
Amen.
至于儿子的新娘
As bride for his son,
长腿选择了他的对手
Longshanks had chosen the daughter of his rival,
法国国王的女儿
the King of France.
人们都说如果王妃想怀孕
It was widely whispered that for the princess to conceive,
长腿恐怕要亲自上阵才行
Longshanks would have to do the honors himself.
那也许才是他一直以来所期望的
That may have been what he had in mind all along.
苏格兰  是我的土地
Scotland. My land.
法国人会向任何强国屈服
The French will grovel to anyone with strength,
但如果我们不能统治全岛
but how will they believe our strength
他们又怎会相信我们的强大
when we cannot rule the whole of our own island?
我儿子呢
Where is my son?
请您原谅  陛下  他让我替他来
Your pardon, milord. He asked me to come in his stead.
我让他来  而他派来了你
I sent for him, and he sends you.
需要我离开吗  陛下
Shall I leave, milord?
如果我死后他想让他的王后来统治
If he wants his queen to rule when I am gone,
那你就留下吧  学习一下如何统治
then, by all means, stay and learn how.
请吧
Please.
贵族们
Nobles.
贵族是打开苏格兰的关键
Nobles are the key to the door of Scotland.
分一些北方的土地给我们的贵族
Grant our nobles lands in the north,
分一些英格兰的土地给他们的贵族
give their nobles estates here in England,
让他们贪婪到无法反抗我们
and make them too greedy to oppose us.
但  陛下  我们的贵族不愿离开家园
But, sire, our nobles will be reluctant to uproot.
新的土地意味着新的赋税
New lands mean new taxes,
他们已经为在法国的战争而缴税
and they're already taxed for the war in France.
是吗
Are they?
苏格兰的问题就在于苏格兰人太多了
The trouble with Scotland is that it's full of Scots.
也许是时候恢复一个古老的习俗了
Perhaps the time has come to reinstitute an old custom.
授予他们初夜权
Grant them prima nocte.
初夜
First night.
在他们土地上居住的平民女孩  若要结婚
When any common girl inhabiting their lands is married,
我们的贵族将在她结婚的当夜
our nobles shall have sexual
享有与她发生性关系的权利
rights to her on the night of her wedding.
如果不能把他们赶走  那就让他们变种
If we can't get them out, we'll breed them out.
这会吸引我们想要的贵族去苏格兰
That should fetch just the kind of lords we want to Scotland,
无论有没有赋税
taxes or no taxes.
-绝妙的办法  陛下  -是吗
- A most excellent idea, sire. - Is it?
爱丁堡
苏格兰贵族正在爱丁堡聚集召开会议
Now in Edinburgh were gathered the council of Scottish nobles.
其中第十七世伯爵  罗伯特·布鲁斯
Among these was Robert, the 17th Earl of Bruce,
他是苏格兰王位的有力竞争者
a leading contender for the crown of Scotland.
我听说长腿批准了初夜权
I hear that Longshanks has granted prima nocte.
很明显是想吸引更多他的支持者到这儿来
Clearly meant to draw more of his supporters here.
我父亲认为
My father believes that
我们必须骗取长腿的信任
we must lull Longshanks into our confidence
既不支持也不反对他的法令
by neither supporting his decree nor opposing it.
聪明的计划
A wise plan.
你父亲怎么样  我们都很想他
And how is your father? We missed him at the council.
他在法国的事务无法脱身
His affairs in France keep him long overdue.
但他向大家问好
But he sends his greetings,
他说我可以代表布鲁斯家族以及苏格兰
and he says that I speak for all of the Bruces and for Scotland.
都结束了
It's all over now.
你的石头掉了
You've dropped your rock.
这是男子气概的考验
Test of manhood.
你赢了
You win.
那就当做对士兵的考验好了
Call it a test of soldiery, then.
英格兰人不许我们用武器训练
The English won't let us train with weapons,
所以我们就用石头
so we train with stones.
对士兵的考验不在他的臂膀  而是在头脑
The test of a soldier is not in his arm. It's here.
不  是在这里
No. It's here.
你是哈米什吗
Hamish?
给你  孩子
Here you go, son.
给他演示一下
Show him how.
加油  哈米什
Come on, Hamish!
你绝不可能打败哈米什
You'll never beat Hamish.
加油啊  伙计
Come on there, boy!
我的好孩子
My boy!
扔得不错
That's a good throw.
是  是啊
Aye. Aye, it was.
我在想紧要关头时你还能扔得好吗
I was wondering if you could do that when it matters.
比如说在打仗的时候
As it matters in battle.
你能用那杀死一个敌人吗
Could you crush a man with that throw?
我可以把你像虫子一样碾碎
I could crush you like a worm.
-是吗  -当然
- You could? - Aye.
那来试试吧
Well, then, do it.
你们想看他把我像虫子一样碾碎吗
Would you like to see him crush me like a worm?
想
Aye.
-来吧  -你会躲的
- Come do it. - You'll move.
我不会的
I will not.
好吧
Right.
他会躲开的
He'll move.
加油  哈米什
Come on, Hamish.
加油啊  孩子
Come on there, boy!
干得漂亮
Well done!
干得漂亮  小华莱士
Fine display, young Wallace.
你还好吗
Are you all right?
你看起来有点儿站不稳
You look a wee bit shaky.
我应该记住小时候扔石头的事来着
I should have remembered the rocks.
是啊  你应该记住的
Aye, you should have.
起来吧  大个子
Get up, you big heap.
很高兴再见到你
It's good to see you again.
我也是  欢迎回家
Aye. Welcome home.
-打到我的头了  -你该躲开的
- Got my head. - Well, you should have moved.
威廉  能跟我跳支舞吗
William, will you dance with me?
当然了
Of course I will.
我来行使我的初夜权
I've come to claim the right of prima nocte.
作为这片土地的领主
As lord of these lands,
我将以占有新娘初夜的方式
I will bless this marriage by taking the bride
为这段婚姻赐福
into my bed on the first night of her union.
上帝啊  你不能那么做
By God, you will not!
这是我的贵族特权
It is my noble right.
晚上好  先生
Good evening, sir.
小华莱士
Young Wallace.
非常美好的夜晚啊  是吗
Grand soft evening, huh?
是啊  真美好
Aye, it's that.
我在想我能否跟您的女儿说句话
I was wondering if I might have a word with your daughter.
你要跟她说什么
What do you want to have a word with her about?
这个嘛
Well...
梅伦  你愿意
Murron, would you like to
在这个美妙的夜晚跟我一起骑马吗
come and ride with me on this fine evening?
这个天气吗  你疯了吧
In this? You're out of your mind.
这是多好的苏格兰式天气啊  夫人
It's good Scottish weather, madam.
雨都是直直地下  没有风
The rain is falling straight down.
只是稍微有点儿倾斜
Slightly to the side, like.
-她不能跟你去  -不行吗
- She can't go with you. - No?
反正现在不行
No the now, anyway.
-现在不行  -现在不行吗
- No the now. - No the now?
回见
We'll see you later.
天气正好  雨也不怎么下了
The weather's just fine. It's hardly raining.
你没听到我说什么吗
Did you not hear what I said?
-梅伦  -梅伦  回...
- Murron! - Murron! Get...
她随你
It's you she takes after.
过去这么久了  你怎么认出我的
How did you know me after so long?
我没认出你
I didn't.
只是  我看见你一直盯着我看
It's just... I saw you staring at me,
但我不知道你是谁
and I didn't know who you were.
抱歉  我想我是盯着你看了
I'm sorry. I suppose I was.
你有在雨中跟陌生人一起骑马的习惯吗
Are you in the habit of riding off in the rain with strangers?
那样才能让你离开啊
It was the best way to make you leave.
我要是能有勇气再邀请你一次的话
If I can ever work up the courage to ask you again,
我会先给你写一封信
I'll send you a written warning first.
那没什么帮助  我不识字
That wouldn't do you much good. I can't read.
-你不识字吗  -是的
- Can you not? - No.
这可是我们该弥补的  不是吗
Well, that's something we shall have to remedy, isn't it?
-你想教我认字吗  -如果你愿意
- You're going to teach me to read, then? - If you like.
-当然  -认哪种语言
- Aye. - In what language?
你现在是在炫耀了
You're showing off now.
是啊  佩服了吧
That's right. Are you impressed yet?
没  怎么  我该佩服吗
No. Why? Should I be?
是啊
因为每一天我都在想着你
你倒立着再说一遍  我就服了你
Do that standing on your head, and I'll be impressed.
我的苏格兰短裙会飞起来  但我会试试
My kilt will fly up, but I'll try it.
天哪  你游历期间真是一点礼仪也没学到
God, you certainly didn't learn any manners on your travels.
法国人和罗马人的礼仪比我还糟
The French and the Romans have far worse manners than I.
你还去过罗马吗
You've been to Rome?
是的   阿盖尔带我去朝圣
Aye, Argyle took me on a pilgrimage.
那是什么样的
What was it like?
都没有你美丽
那是什么意思
What does that mean?
很美
Beautiful.
但我属于这里
But I belong here.
梅伦  快进来
Murron? Come in now.
先生  我知道昨晚
Sir, I know it was strange of me
我邀请梅伦一起骑马很奇怪
to invite Murron to ride last night,
但我向你保证
but I assure you...
我们不是为麦克克劳恩的女儿而来
MacClannough's daughter is another matter.
我来是叫你去参加我们的集会
I've come to fetch you to our meeting.
-什么样的集会  -秘密的那种
- What kind of meeting? - The secret kind.
你们的集会不过是在浪费时间  坎贝尔
Your meetings are a waste of time, Campbell.
你父亲是名斗士也是一位爱国者
Your father was a fighter and a patriot.
我知道我父亲是什么样的
I know who my father was.
我是回来种田的
I came back home to raise crops and,
如果可以  组建一个家庭
God willing, a family.
-如果能平静地生活  我会的  -走吧
- If I can live in peace, I will. - Go on.
你是说你不会惹麻烦吗
You say you want to stay out of the troubles?
是的
Aye.
如果你能证明  就可以向我女儿求爱
If you can prove it, you may court my daughter.
在你证明之前  我的答案是不行
Until you prove it, my answer's no.
不行吗
No?
不行  华莱士  不行
No, Wallace. No.
-我刚才还没有证明吗  -没有
- Didn't I just prove it? - No!
-没有吗  -没有
- No? - No!
当然了  经营农场有很多工作要做
Of course, running a farm's a lot of work,
等我儿子们到了就好多了
but that will all change when my sons arrive.
你有孩子了
So you've got children?
还没有  但我希望你能给我生几个
Not yet, but I was hoping that you could help me with that.
所以你是想要我嫁给你了
So you want me to marry you, then?
是有点突然  不过是的
It's a bit sudden, but all right.
你就是这样求婚的吗
Is that what you call a proposal?
我爱你  一直都是
I love you. Always have.
我想娶你
I want to marry you.
这算是答应了吗
Is that a yes?
-是的  我答应了  -是吗
- Aye, that's a yes. - It is?
我们最好快点  他等着呢
We best hurry. He'll be waiting.
-等等  -你去哪
- Wait. - Where are you going?
-这是什么  -你会知道的
- What's that? - You'll see.
神父
Father.
我将用我的一生来爱你
I will love you my whole life,
别无她人
you and no other.
我也爱你
And I you,
别无他人  直到永远
you and no other, forever.
我什么时候能再见到你
When am I going to see you again?
今晚可以吗
Tonight?
-不行  -为什么
- I can't. - Why not?
我爸开始怀疑了
My dad's growing suspicious.
开始怀疑了是吗
Growing suspicious, is he?
并没有什么关系  不是吗
Wouldn't have anything to do with that, would it?
什么时候
When? When? When?
-什么时候  -今晚
- When? - Tonight.
-今晚见  -今晚见
- Tonight. - Tonight.
打起精神来  军士
Look lively, Sergeant.
你去哪儿  姑娘
Where are you going, lassie?
看起来挺沉
That looks heavy.
-我帮你拿  -不用  没关系
- Let me help you with it. - No. It's fine.
我不会抢走的
I'm not going to steal it.
你让我想起我家里的女儿了
You remind me of my daughter back home.
你好啊  姑娘
Hello, lassie.
不  不
No! No!
小声点  斯迈思
Keep it quiet, Smythe.
臭婊子
You bitch!
你没事吧
Are you all right?
没事吧  走
All right? Come on.
-你没事吧  -没事
- Are you all right? - Aye.
你没事吧
Are you all right?
-能骑马吗  -可以
- Can you ride? - Aye.
给我回来  畜生
Come back here, you bastard!
拉响警报
Raise the alarm!
快帮忙
Help!
在树林见  快走
Meet me at the grove. Ride!
他们要跑了
They're getting away!
去后面
Go round back!
抓住她
Get her!
快点
Come on!
臭婊子
You bitch!
梅伦
Murron?
Murron!
你们都很清楚
All of you know full well
我一直煞费苦心
the great pains I've always taken
尽量在执行律法时
never to be too strict,
不会过于严苛
too rigid with the application of our laws.
然而结果呢
And as a consequence,
我们不是该学会
have we not learned to live together
如何和谐共处吗
in relative peace and harmony?
你们就是用今天这种无法无天的行为
And this day's lawlessness is
来回报我的仁慈的
how you repay my leniency!
你们让我别无选择
Well, you leave me with little choice.
攻击国王的士兵
An assault on the King's soldiers
等同于攻击国王本人
is the same as an assault on the King himself.
现在
Now,
让那个莽夫放马过来吧
let this scrapper come to me.
阁下
Sir!
在那儿
There.
下士
Corporal.
弓箭手上塔楼  马上
Some archers on the tower. Now!
别动  父亲
Hold still, father.
你个蠢货
You're an idiot, boy!
父亲  你没事吧
Father, you all right?
华莱士之子
MacAulish.
MacAulish!
华莱士之子  华莱士之子
MacAulish! MacAulish!
华莱士  华莱士
Wallace! Wallace!
华莱士  华莱士  华莱士
Wallace! Wallace! Wallace!
愿她的灵魂
Anima ejus
及所有虔诚的灵魂
et anime omnium fidelium defunctorum
在主的恩赐下
per misericordiam Dei
安息
requiescant in pace.
还等什么  孩子
What you waiting for, boy?
给你  你能做到  我按住他
Here. You can do it. I'll hold him down.
给你  你能做到
Here. You can do it.
我按住他
I'll hold him down.
直接倒在伤口上  孩子
Pour it straight in the wound, boy.
我知道这算是浪费了一瓶好酒
I know it seems like a waste of good whiskey.
让我放纵下吧
Indulge me.
按住他  按住他
Hold him. Hold him.
按住他  现在放开他
Hold him. Now let him go.
对不起  对不起
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
早晨把你叫醒全靠这个  孩子
That'll wake you up in the morning, boy.
有人来了
There's somebody coming!
拿好武器
Arm yourselves!
有人来了
There's somebody coming.
麦格雷戈家族  隔壁峡谷的
MacGregors, from the next glen.
我们听说了发生的事情
We heard about what was happening.
你们这帮傻瓜
We don't want you Amadans
可不能不带我们玩
thinking you can have your fun without us.
-没错  -对
- That's right. - Aye.
回去吧
Go home.
我们有些人已身涉其中
Some of us are in this.
无能为力
Can't help that now.
但你们没必要这样  回去吧
But you can help yourselves. Go home.
等那些城堡里来的
We'll have no homes left
英国部队来把我们的家烧掉之后
when the English garrison from the castle
我们就无家可归了
comes through and burns us out.
-他们一定会的  -没错
- And they will. - Aye.
欢迎加入
Welcome.
侦察队回来了  大人
Patrol returning, milord!
情况如何
So what news?
我派了一百名士兵去拉纳克
I have dispatched 100 soldiers to Lanark.
他们现在应该要回来了
They will be returning now!
他们是穿成这样吗
Were they dressed like this?
事实上也就五十人
Actually, it was more like 50.
速度解决
Make it quick.
记得我吗
You remember me?
我从没伤害过她  这是我的权利
I never did her any harm. It was my right.
你的权利
Your right?
我是来行使一名丈夫的权利的
Well, I'm here to claim the right of a husband!
我叫威廉·华莱士
I am William Wallace,
你们剩下的人会被赦免
and the rest of you will be spared.
回去英格兰  告诉那里的人
Go back to England and tell them there
苏格兰儿女不再是他们的子民
that Scotland's daughters and her sons are yours no more.
告诉他们苏格兰自由了
Tell them Scotland is free.
把这烧了
Burn it.
射得好  大人
Good job, milord.
苏格兰反叛者攻击了我们的一处驻地
Scottish rebels have routed one of my garrisons
并杀害了贵族领主
and murdered the noble lord.
我听说了
I heard.
这个华莱士只是一介强盗而已
This Wallace is a brigand, nothing more.
那你会怎么对付这个强盗呢
And how would you deal with this brigand?
跟对付一般的窃贼一样
Like any common thief.
让当地治安官逮捕他并做出相应的惩罚
Have the local magistrate arrest him and punish him accordingly.
你们退下
Leave us.
华莱士已经杀了治安官
Wallace has already killed the magistrate
并控制了城镇
and taken control of the town.
起来
Stand up.
站起来
到早上
In the morning,
我去法国促使他们承认我们的权利
I depart for France to press our rights there,
留你在这里镇压这起小叛乱
and I leave you here to quell this little rebellion.
明白了吗  懂了吗
Understood? Is it?
总有一天  你将成为国王
One day, you will be a King,
至少试着拿出点国王的样子来
at least try to act like one.
别碰我
Get away from me!
传召我的军事议会
Convene my military council.
希望你丈夫去苏格兰
见到华莱士
然后你就会成为寡妇了
在那儿
There!
追
After them.
不要做无谓的抵抗
No point resisting.
你们寡不敌众  已被包围
You're outnumbered and trapped.
其他人呢  华莱士在哪
Now, where are the rest of you? Where's Wallace?
父亲
Father?
进来  进来
Come in. Come in.
发生了叛乱
A rebellion has begun.
谁带领的
Under whom?
一个叫威廉·华莱士的平民
A commoner named William Wallace.
你要支持这起叛乱
You will embrace this rebellion.
在我们北部领土上支持它
Support it from our lands in the north.
我将在我们南部地区
I will gain English favor
下令不支持
by condemning it and
并声讨它以赢得英国的支持
ordering it opposed from our lands in the south.
坐吧  待一会儿
Sit down. Stay awhile.
这个华莱士
This Wallace,
他连骑士都不是  但他一腔热血
he doesn't even have a knighthood, but he fights with passion,
能够鼓舞士气
and he inspires.
你也想像他那样叛变起义吗
And you wish to charge off and fight as he did?
我也想
So would I.
也许是时候了
Well, maybe it's time.
现在是保命的时候
It is time to survive.
你是罗伯特·布鲁斯十七世
You're the 17th Robert Bruce.
之前的前十六世
The 16 before you passed you
能将土地与封号传给你就是因为他们没有闹事
land and title because they didn't charge in.
-召集贵族会议  -他们只会空谈
- Call a meeting of the nobles. - They do nothing but talk.
没错
Rightly so.
他们在英格兰也有着
They're as rich in English
和在苏格兰一样高贵的封号和富裕的土地
titles and lands as they are in Scottish.
我们也一样
Just as we are.
你羡慕这个威廉·华莱士
You admire this man, this William Wallace.
决不妥协的人总是容易让人敬佩
Uncompromising men are easy to admire.
他有勇气  狗也有
He has courage, so does a dog.
然而真正成就贵族的
But it is exactly the ability to compromise
是妥协与让步
that makes a man noble.
要知道
And understand this,
长腿爱德华是英格兰王位上
Edward Longshanks is the most ruthless king
最残忍无情的国王
ever to sit on the throne of England,
除非我们也一样残忍
and none of us and nothing of
否则我们以及苏格兰的一切都将不复存在
Scotland will remain unless we are as ruthless.
聆听我们贵族的意见
Give ear to our nobles.
了解他们的想法是获得王位的关键
Knowing their minds is the key to the throne.
等等  等等  看
Wait. Wait. Look.
-这要出来  这要放左边  -当然了
- This is out, and this is left. - Of course.
继续走
Carry on.
走啊
Carry on!
等国王回来会让那些漂亮衣服给他们陪葬
苏格兰一片混乱
你丈夫正秘密派军北上
你怎么知道
我昨晚睡了一个军事议会成员
他真不该在床上透露秘密
是啊
英国人真是不懂舌头的用途
这支苏格兰叛军  那个华莱士
他是要为一个女人复仇吗
我都快忘了
一个治安官想抓他
发现他有一个秘密情人
于是治安官割了那女孩的喉咙
以此激怒华莱士出手
他也的确出手了
了解到他对已逝爱人的感情
他们又谋划了其他方法
他们破坏了他爸爸和哥哥的坟墓
并在他爱人的墓地旁设下埋伏
但他杀出了陷阱
带着爱人的尸体去了一个秘密的地方
这就是爱  不是吗
爱
我怎么会知道
要知道  最终
You know, eventually,
长腿会派整个北方军队来对付我们
Longshanks will send his whole northern army against us.
重骑兵  武装战马
Heavy cavalry, armored horse.
撼动大地
Shake the very ground.
他们会把我们活活踩死
They'll ride right over us.
阿盖尔叔叔曾经谈起过
Uncle Argyle used to talk about it,
重骑兵是如何的无往不胜
how no army had ever stood up to a charge of heavy horse.
那我们该怎么做
So what do we do?
游击战  用高地人的办法
Hit, run, hide, the Highland way.
我们造些长矛
We'll make spears.
上百杆
Hundreds of them.
很长的长矛  两人高
Long spears, twice as long as a man.
-要那么长吗  -对
- That long? - Aye.
有的人要比其他人长些
Some men are longer than others.
你妈又跟你说我的事迹了
Your mother been telling you stories about me again.
志愿军来了
Volunteers coming in!
威廉·华莱士
William Wallace,
我们来为你作战  誓死效忠
we've come to fight and to die for you.
起来吧  伙计  我可不是教皇
Stand up, man. I'm not the Pope.
我叫法奥敦  我愿为你而战
My name is Faudron. My sword is yours.
我给你带了这个
I brought you this.
我们搜过他们的身了
We checked them for arms.
我给你带了这个
I brought you this.
-我妻子为你做的  -谢谢
- My wife made it for you. - Thank you.
他  不可能是威廉·华莱士
Him? That can't be William Wallace.
我比他帅
I'm prettier than this man.
好了  圣父  我问问他
All right, Father. I'll ask him.
若我为你出生入死
If I risk my neck for you,
我有机会杀英国人吗
will I get a chance to kill Englishmen?
你的圣父是先人的灵魂
Is your Father a ghost,
还是你能与上帝交流
or do you converse with the Almighty?
为了找到旗鼓相当的对手
In order to find his equal,
爱尔兰人被迫与上帝交谈
an Irishman is forced to talk to God.
什么  圣父
Yes, Father?
上帝说不要转移话题
The Almighty says don't change the subject,
回答那该死的问题
just answer the fucking question.
说话注意些
Mind your tongue.
爱尔兰疯子
Insane Irish.
至少足够聪明躲过检查带匕首进来  老头
Smart enough to get a dagger past your guards, old man.
这是我朋友  爱尔兰人
That's my friend, Irishman,
而我的答案是肯定的
and the answer to your question is yes.
你为我而战  就能杀到英国人
You fight for me, you get to kill the English.
好极了
Excellent!
我叫斯蒂芬
Stephen is my name.
在我的岛上我可是头号通缉犯
I'm the most wanted man on my island,
不过当然我没在岛上
except I'm not on my island, of course.
真是遗憾
More's the pity.
你的岛  你是说爱尔兰吗
Your island? You mean Ireland?
没错  那是我的
Yeah. It's mine.
你真是个疯子
You're a madman.
看来我来对地方了
I've come to the right place, then.
确定不是上帝派我来保护你的吗
Sure didn't the Almighty send me to watch your back?
反正我也不喜欢他
I didn't like him anyway.
他脑袋不对劲
He wasn't right in the head.
威廉
William!
来了几个传信员
It's several runners!
英格兰派军队往斯特灵来了
The English are advancing an army toward Stirling.
贵族们达成一致了吗
Do the nobles rally?
罗伯特·布鲁斯还有绝大多数人都不会参战
Robert the Bruce and most of the others will not commit to battle,
但事情已经传开了
but word has spread,
高地人自己来了
and the Highlanders are coming down on their own.
对  成百上千
Aye, in droves of hundreds and thousands.
准备好一战了吗
Are you ready for a war?
斯特灵
-什么情况  -他们人太多了
- Well, what news? - We're outnumbered,
至少是我们的三倍
at least three to one.
-那有多少匹马  -三百  或许更多
- How many horse, then? - Three hundred. Maybe more.
三百匹重装战马
Three hundred heavy horse?
-我们必须尽量谈判  -谁是指挥官
- We must try to negotiate. - Well, who is in command?
-他有猩红色的V型图案吗  -是的
-Did he have a scarlet chevron? -Aye, he did.
我们依然可以谈判
We can still negotiate.
他们在说什么
What are they talking about?
我听不清  但看上去不妙
I can't hear, but it doesn't look good.
贵族们会谈判的
The nobles will negotiate.
他们会达成协议  之后我们就打道回府
They'll do a deal, then we go home.
如果不然  我们就进攻
If not, we charge.
三百匹重装战马  我们没胜算的
Three hundred heavy horse, we've no chance.
太多了
So many.
我来战斗不是为了让他们拥有更多土地
I didn't come here to fight so they could own more lands.
以后我还得给他们干活
Then I'll have to work for them.
我也不是
Nor me.
好了伙计们  我不会为了这些混蛋赴死的
All right, lads! I'm not dying for these bastards.
我们回家吧
Let's go home!
停下  伙计们  别逃跑
Stop, men! Do not flee!
等我们谈判好了再走
Wait until we've negotiated!
是威廉·华莱士
William Wallace.
不可能  他不够高
Can't be. Not tall enough.
上帝说这一定是场上流的战争
The Almighty says this must be a fashionable fight.
引来了这么多上流人物
It's drawn the finest people.
你为什么不行礼
Where is thy salute?
对你亲临战场  我向你致谢
For presenting yourselves on this battlefield, I give you thanks.
这是我们的军队
This is our army.
要加入  你得效忠于我
To join it, you give homage.
我效忠于苏格兰
I give homage to Scotland,
如果这是你的军队
and if this is your army
为什么它要散了
why does it go?
我们来不是为了他们而战
We didn't come here to fight for them!
回家  英格兰军队的人太多了
Home! The English are too many.
苏格兰的孩子们
Sons of Scotland,
我是威廉·华莱士
I am William Wallace.
威廉·华莱士有七英尺高
William Wallace is seven feet tall.
是的  我听说了
Yes, I've heard.
他杀的人数以百计
He kills men by the hundreds,
他要是在这  会把英军杀得屁滚尿流
and if he were here, he'd consume the English
就用双眼射出的火球
with fireballs from his eyes
和屁股里放出的闪电
and bolts of lightning from his arse.
我是威廉·华莱士
I am William Wallace,
我看到一整支由我同胞组成的军队
and I see a whole army of my countrymen
在此抵抗暴政
here in defiance of tyranny.
你们身为自由人来此战斗
You've come to fight as free men.
而此时此刻你们是自由的
And free men you are.
你们要用那自由去做什么
What will you do with that freedom?
你们会战斗吗
Will you fight?
不会  不会  不会
No! No! No!
战斗  和那种军队战斗  绝不
Fight? Against that? No!
我们会逃跑  会活下去
We will run, and we will live.
没错
Aye.
战斗  你也许会死
Fight, and you may die.
逃跑  你会活下去
Run, and you'll live.
至少能活一阵
At least a while.
然后许多年后躺在床上奄奄一息
And dying in your beds many years from now,
那时你会不会想用你苟且偷生来的岁月去换取
would you be willing to trade all the days from this day to that
一个机会  就这么一个机会
for one chance, just one chance,
回到这里  告诉我们的敌人
to come back here and tell our enemies
他们或许可以夺走我们的生命
that they may take our lives,
但他们永远无法夺走我们的自由
but they'll never take our freedom!
苏格兰万岁
Alba gu brath!
在我看来  他们相当乐观
They seem quite optimistic to me.
或许他们真的愿意战斗
Maybe they do want to fight.
交战也许是不可避免的  大人
Confrontation might be a foregone conclusion, milord,
但尽管如此
but, nonetheless,
我认为我们应先传达国王的条件
I think we should deliver the king's terms.
国王的条件  他绝对不会兑现的
The king's terms? He'll never live up to them.
大人  我认为...
Milord, I think...
好吧  把条件说给他们听
All right. Offer them the terms.
他们过来了  我们要过去与他们会面吗
They're coming out. Shall we go and meet them?
-我来跟他们谈  同意吗  -同意
- Let me do the talking. Agreed? - Agreed.
讲得不错
Fine speech.
我们现在怎么做
Now what do we do?
做你自己就好
Just be yourselves.
你要去哪里
Where are you going?
我去挑衅下
I'm going to pick a fight.
看来我们没白全副武装
Well, we didn't get dressed up for nothing.
莫尔奈  洛克林  克雷格.
Mornay, Lochlan, Craig.
以下是国王的条件
Here are the king's terms.
将你们的军队带离战场
Lead this army off the field,
他会赏给你们每个人约克郡的土地
and he will give you each estates in Yorkshire,
包括世袭封号
including hereditary title,
据此你们要付...
from which you will pay...
据此你们要交付年税...
From which you will pay him an annual duty...
我有个提议给你
I have an offer for you.
切尔汉姆  这位是威廉·华莱士
Cheltham, this is William Wallace.
据此你们向国王要交付年税...
From which you will pay the king an annual duty...
我说了我有个提议给你
I said I have an offer for you.
你是在藐视休战的旗帜么
You disrespect a banner of truce?
他的国王的旗帜  当然了
From his king? Absolutely.
以下是苏格兰的条件
Here are Scotland's terms.
降下你们的旗帜  直接返回英格兰
Lower your flags and march straight back to England,
在路过的每户人家前停下
stopping at every home you pass by to beg forgiveness
为百年来的偷窃  强奸和谋杀行为祈求宽恕
for 100 years of theft, rape and murder.
照做  你的人就能活下去
Do that and your men shall live.
否则  今天就是你们的死期
Do it not and every one of you will die today.
你们毫无胜算
You are outmatched.
你们没有重骑兵
You have no heavy cavalry.
两个世纪以来  没有军队曾打败...
ln two centuries, no army has won...
我还没说完
I'm not finished!
在我们放你们走之前
Before we let you leave,
你的指挥官必须穿过这片战场
your commander must cross that field,
在我们的军队面前现身
present himself before this army,
将他的头置于两腿中间
put his head between his legs,
亲他自己的屁股
and kiss his own arse.
要我说他没以前那么亲切了
I'd say that was rather less cordial than he was used to.
你们准备好  照我说的做
You be ready and do exactly as I say.
看我信号
On my signal,
骑马从我们背后绕过去  攻击他们的侧翼
ride round behind our position and flank them.
我们不应该分散兵力
We must not divide our forces.
照做  并且让英格兰军队看见你这么做了
Do it and let the English see you do it.
他们会认为我们逃跑了
They'll think we run away.
灭掉他们的弓手  我在中间与你们会合
Take out their archers. I'll meet you in the middle.
好的  来吧
Right. Come on.
傲慢无礼的杂种
Insolent bastard.
我要把这个华莱士的心脏挖出来放盘子上
I want this Wallace's heart on a plate.
弓手准备
Archers.
弓手  弓手  弓手
Archers! Archers! Archers!
-弓手  前进  -弓手  前进
- Archers, forward! - Archers, forward!
你们这群混蛋
You bastards!
放箭
Loose!
主告诉我他能助我逃离这场混乱
The Lord tells me he can get me out of this mess,
但他很确信你完蛋了
but he's pretty sure you're fucked.
-准备  -放箭
- Ready! - Loose!
骑马走
Ride!
看吧  所有骑着马的苏格兰人都逃走了
See, every Scot with a horse is fleeing.
我们的重骑兵会像碾过草地一样碾死他们
Our cavalry will ride them down like grass.
派出骑兵
Send the horse.
全力进攻
Full attack.
稳住
Steady!
别动
Hold!
现在
Now!
派步兵上
Send the infantry.
-大人...  -你去领兵
- Milord... - You lead them!
撤退
Retreat!
混蛋
Bastard!
好了
All right.
华莱士  华莱士
Wallace! Wallace!
我封你为威廉·华莱士爵士
I knight thee Sir William Wallace.
威廉爵士  以天主之名
Sir William, in the name of God,
我们宣布指派你为苏格兰的守护者和护国公
we declare and appoint thee guardian and high protector of Scotland
任命你的队长们为你的副官
and thy captains as aides-de-camp.
起身接受祝贺吧
Stand and be recognized.
有人知道他的政治立场吗
Does anyone know his politics?
不知道  但他在平民心中的分量可颠覆一切
No, but his weight with the commoners could unbalance everything.
巴里奥家族肯定会拍他马屁  我们也得照做
The Balliols will kiss his arse, and so we must.
威廉爵士
Sir William.
Sir William,
既然您和您的队长们都来自一个
in as much as you and your captains hail from a region
长久以来众所周知支持巴里奥家族的地区
long known to support the Balliol clan,
我们能否请您继续支持
may we invite you to continue your support
并捍卫我们的合法权利
and uphold our rightful claim?
该死的巴里奥家族
Damn the Balliol clan!
他们都是长腿的走狗
They're all Longshanks' men!
先生们  先生们
Gentlemen. Gentlemen!
-是时候决定谁是国王了  -等等
- Now is the time to declare a king. - Wait!
你是说你准备承认我们的正统继承权了
And you're prepared to recognize our legitimate succession, I take it.
你们才是不肯支持真正国王的人
You're the ones who won't support the rightful king.
你当初写的时候那些就是谎言
Those were lies when you first wrote them.
-不  -这是事实
- No. - That's the truth.
我要求认可这些文件
I demand recognition of these documents!
这些文件在你当初写的时候就是谎言
These documents were lies when you wrote them!
先生们  请静一静  先生们
Gentlemen, please! Gentlemen!
静一静  先生们
Please, gentlemen!
等等  威廉爵士  你要去哪里
Wait! Sir William, where are you going?
我们击败了英格兰军  但他们会卷土重来
We have beaten the English, but they'll come back
因为你们不愿团结一致
because you won't stand together.
你要做什么
What will you do?
我要入侵英格兰
I will invade England
在英格兰人自己的土地上打败他们
and defeat the English on their own ground.
入侵  那不可能
lnvade? That's impossible.
为什么
Why?
为什么不可能
Why is that impossible?
你们忙着
You're so concerned with
争夺长腿桌上的残羹冷炙
squabbling for the scraps from Longshanks' table
却忽视了上天赐予的更好的权利
that you've missed your God-given right to something better.
我们是不同的
There's a difference between us.
你们认为这个国家的人民之所以存在
You think the people of this country exist
是为了使你们拥有如今的地位
to provide you with position.
我认为你们的地位之所以存在
I think your position exists
是为了让这些人民获得自由
to provide those people with freedom,
而我会确保他们拥有这自由
and I go to make sure that they have it.
等等
Wait!
我敬佩你刚才说的话
I respect what you said,
但你要记住这些人拥有土地和城堡
but remember that these men have lands and castles.
风险太大了
lt's much to risk.
那在战场上流血的平民
And the common man that bleeds on the battlefield,
他冒的风险就小了
does he risk less?
不
No.
但从上到下  这个国家完全没有主权意识
But from top to bottom, this country has got no sense of itself.
它的贵族们为英格兰人效忠
Its nobles share allegiance with England.
家族之间彼此争斗
Its clans war with each other.
-没错  -没错
- Aye. - Aye.
如果你腹背受敌
lf you make enemies on both sides of the border,
你只有死路一条
you'll end up dead.
人终有一死  只看是如何死  又为何而死
We all end up dead. It's just a question of how and why.
我不是懦夫
I'm not a coward.
我与你所求相同  但我们需要贵族
I want what you want, but we need the nobles.
-我们需要他们  -没错
- We need them? - Aye.
贵族
Nobles.
现在  告诉我  成为贵族意味着什么
Now, tell me, what does that mean, to be noble?
你的封号让你有资格成为我们国家的国王
Your title gives you claim to the throne of our country,
但人们追随的不是封号
but men don't follow titles.
他们追随的是勇气
They follow courage.
你的名字家喻户晓
Now, our people know you.
无论是贵族还是平民  都尊敬你
Noble and common, they respect you,
如果你愿意带领他们获得自由
and if you would just lead them to freedom,
他们会追随你
they'd follow you.
我也会
And so would l.
该死
Damn it!
我那爱玩鸡奸的王子堂弟告诉我
My sodomite cousin the prince tells me
他没有军队借我了
he has no troops to lend,
英格兰北部的城镇没有一个不在求援的
and every town in northern England is begging for help.
-他进军了  -朝哪个城镇
- He advances! - To which town?
朝这里  大人
To here, milord.
将食物和补给收入城内
Bring the food and provisions inside.
加倍城墙上的守卫  封锁大门  快去
Double the wall guards, seal the gate. Now!
把补给收入城内
Bring in the provisions!
大人  如果您现在离开  我们能带您出去
Sir, we can get you out if you leave now.
我不想告诉我的叔叔
I'm not about to tell my uncle
我把他英格兰北部最大的城丢了
I've lost him the greatest city in northern England.
我们上
Come on!
为国王让路
Make way for the king!
这不是你的错
lt's not your fault.
勇敢地面对他
Stand up to him!
我不仅会勇敢地面对他
I will stand up to him and more.
北部有什么消息
What news of the north?
没有新消息  陛下
Nothing new, Your Majesty.
我们已派遣骑士加快传信速度
We've sent riders to speed any word.
我在法国时听到了消息
I heard the word in France,
我在那竭力为你扩张未来帝国的版图
where I was fighting to expand your future kingdom.
吾儿  消息说
The word, my son,
我们北部军队已全军覆没
is that our entire northern army is annihilated,
而你毫无作为
and you have done nothing.
我已下令征兵  陛下
I have ordered conscriptions, sir.
他们已集合完毕  整装待发
They're assembled and ready to depart.
打扰一下  陛下  约克郡有紧急消息
Excuse me, sire, but there's a very urgent message from York.
进来
Come.
-退下吧  -谢谢您  陛下
- Leave us. - Thank you, sire.
-华莱士洗劫了约克郡  -什么
- Wallace has sacked York. - What?
华莱士洗劫了约克郡
Wallace has sacked York!
陛下  您的亲侄子
Sire, thy own nephew.
什么样的禽兽才会下此狠手
What beast could do such a thing?
如果他能攻下约克郡
lf he can sack York,
他也可以入侵英格兰腹地
he can invade lower England.
我们会阻止他的
We would stop him!
这个和我说话
Who is this person who
自以为我需要他建议的人是谁
speaks to me as though I needed his advice?
我已任命菲利普为我的高级参谋
I have declared Philip my high counselor.
他能胜任
Is he qualified?
我精通战争艺术和军事战略  陛下
I am skilled in the arts of war and military tactics, sire.
是吗
Are you?
那告诉我  就目前形势
Then tell me, what advice would you offer
你会给出什么建议
on the present situation?
我应该提出休战
I shall offer a truce
收买他
and buy him off.
但谁去和他谈呢  不能是我
But who will go to him? Not I.
如果我倒在那凶手的剑下
If I fell under the sword of that murderer,
篮子里可能就是我的脑袋了
it might be my head in a basket.
我温和的儿子也不行
And not my gentle son.
仅仅是看他一眼
The mere sight of him
都会鼓励我们的敌人拿下整个国家
would only encourage an enemy to take over the whole country.
那我应该派谁去呢
So whom do I send?
派谁去呢
Whom do I send?
我在做梦
I'm dreaming.
对  你在做梦
Yes, you are.
你得醒过来
And you must wake.
我不想醒过来
I don't want to wake.
我想在这陪着你
I want to stay here with you.
我也想陪着你
And I with you,
但你现在必须醒过来
but you must wake now.
醒醒  威廉
Wake up, William.
醒醒
Wake up.
威廉  醒醒  醒醒
William, wake up, wake up.
威廉
William!
来了位皇家使者  打着休战旗
A royal entourage comes, flying banners of truce
还有长腿的军旗
and the standards of Longshanks himself!
我是威尔士王妃
I am the Princess of Wales.
我奉国王之命而来
I come as the king's servant and with his authority.
来干什么
To do what?
来谈谈国王的提议
To discuss the king's proposals.
你愿意和女流之辈谈吗
Will you speak with a woman?
我知道你刚刚被授予骑士爵位
I understand you have recently been given the rank of knight.
没人给过我什么东西
I have been given nothing.
上帝决定了人们的身份
God makes men what they are.
上帝让你去洗劫安宁的城市吗
Did God make you the sacker of peaceful cities,
上帝让你处决国王的外甥  我丈夫的表弟
the executioner of the king's nephew, my husband's own cousin?
约克郡是入侵我国的跳板
York was the staging point for every invasion of my country,
你那皇家表弟在城墙上绞死过
and that royal cousin hanged innocent Scots,
无辜的苏格兰人  甚至连女人和孩子都不放过
even women and children, from the city walls.
上次长腿攻下苏格兰城市时手段更残忍
Longshanks did far worse the last time he took a Scottish city.
他就是个残暴的野蛮人
而且他在撒谎
我从不撒谎
但我确实是个野蛮人
还是你们想说法语
你当面问问你的国王
You ask your king to his face.
问问他
Ask him.
看他能否用眼神说服你相信真相
You see if his eyes can convince you of the truth.
汉密尔顿  退下吧
Hamilton, leave us.
-夫人  -快退下吧
- Milady... - Leave us. Now.
我们就直说吧
Let us talk plainly.
你入侵英格兰
You invade England,
但你不可能征服英格兰全境
but you cannot complete the conquest
这里距离你的大本营太远  补给困难
so far from your shelter and supply.
国王渴望和平
The king desires peace.
长腿渴望和平
Longshanks desires peace?
他对我说的  我发誓
He declares it to me. I swear it.
他提议  你停止进攻
He proposes that you withdraw your attack.
作为回报  他会赐予你封号  领地
In return, he grants you title, estates,
还有一箱金子  由我亲自交给你
and this chest of gold, which I am to pay to you personally.
领地和封号
A lordship and titles.
还有金子
Gold.
然后我就得变成叛徒
That I should become Judas?
和平就是这样产生的
Peace is made in such ways.
奴隶才是这样产生的
Slaves are made in such ways!
上次长腿谈及和平时  我还是个孩子
The last time Longshanks spoke of peace, I was a boy,
许多不愿成为奴隶的苏格兰贵族
and many Scottish nobles, who would not be slaves,
被他所谓的休战引诱
were lured by him, under a flag of truce,
在谷仓里被他绞死
to a barn where he had them hanged.
那时我还很小
I was very young,
但我记得长腿所谓的和平
but I remember Longshanks' notion of peace.
我理解你所经历的痛苦
I understand you have suffered.
我知道你女人的事
I know about your woman.
她是我妻子
She was my wife.
我们秘密结婚
We married in secret
因为我不愿让英格兰领主碰她
because I would not share her with an English lord.
他们为了抓我  把她杀了
They killed her to get to me.
我从没说起过这事
I have never spoken of it.
我也不知道为什么现在告诉你这些  只是
I don't know why I tell you now, expect
我在你身上看见了她的坚强
I see her strength in you.
有一天  你会成为女王
One day, you'll be a queen,
你一定要睁大眼睛
and you must open your eyes.
你告诉国王  威廉·华莱士不接受统治
You tell your king that William Wallace will not be ruled,
只要我还活着  苏格兰人也不会
and nor will any Scot while I live.
我的儿媳妇没被异教徒杀死  安全归来了
My son's loyal wife returns unkilled by the heathen.
他接受我们的收买了吗
So he accepted our bribe?
没有  他不接受
No, he did not.
那他为什么按兵不动
Then why does he stay?
我的侦察兵说  他没进军
My scouts tell me that he has not advanced.
他在约克郡等你
He waits for you at York.
他说他不会再攻击城镇
He says he will attack no more towns or cities
只要你够男人敢去跟他会面
if you are man enough to come and face him.
是吗
Did he?
威尔士弓箭手可以偷偷
The Welsh bowmen will not be detected
绕过他的侧翼抵达这里
arriving so far around his flank.
我们从法国调来的主力
The main force of our armies from France will land here
可以从爱丁堡北部登陆
to the north of Edinburgh.
爱尔兰的新军从西南方进军至此
Conscripts from Ireland will approach from the southwest to here.
威尔士弓箭手  法国军队
Welsh bowmen? Troops from France?
爱尔兰新军
Irish conscripts?
就算你今天调遣  也需要几周集结军队
Even if you dispatch them today, they'd take weeks to assemble.
派你妻子去之前  我就发出了调遣命令
I dispatched them before I sent your wife.
我们的小策略成功了
So our little ruse succeeded.
谢谢
Thank you.
这自负的家伙在约克郡等我的时候
And while this upstart awaits my arrival in York,
我的部队已经到达他身后的爱丁堡了
my forces will have arrived in Edinburgh behind him.
你跟这个华莱士私下谈过
You spoke with this Wallace in private.
告诉我
Tell me,
他是个什么样的人
what kind of man is he?
愚蠢的野蛮人
A mindless barbarian.
不像国王您  陛下
Not a king like you, milord.
你可以回房绣花了
You may return to your embroidery.
当然  陛下
Humbly, milord.
你把金子带回来了吧
You brought back the money, of course.
没有
No.
我把金子分给了孩子们  以平息战争之痛
I gave it to ease the suffering of the children of this war.
你派个女人去  就会这样
That's what happens when you send a woman.
原谅我  陛下
Forgive me, sire.
我觉得这种慷慨可以向那些您打算统治的人
I thought that generosity might demonstrate your greatness
证实您的伟大
to those you mean to rule.
我的伟大会在华莱士回到苏格兰
My greatness will be better demonstrated
却发现他的国家成为灰烬时得到更好的证明
when Wallace returns to Scotland and finds his country in ashes.
威廉
William!
有人骑着马过来了
There's riders approaching!
王妃的贴身侍女
Personal escort of the princess.
对
Aye.
你肯定给她留下了深刻印象
Must have made an impression.
对
Aye.
没觉得你在帐篷里待了那么长时间啊
I didn't think you were in the tent that long.
小姐
Mademoiselle.
女主人给你的信
Un message de ma maîtresse.
谢谢
Merci.
是真的  英国船正从南方逼近
It's true! English ships are moving up from the south!
还不清楚威尔士军队的情况
I don't know about the Welsh yet,
但爱尔兰人已经登陆了
but the Irish have landed!
要不是亲眼看到我真是不敢相信
I had to see it with me own eyes before I could believe it.
爱尔兰人为什么和英国人并肩作战
What the hell are the Irish doing fighting with the English?
我不担心他们
I wouldn't worry about them.
我之前不是说过吗  那是我的岛
Didn't I tell you before? It's my island.
哈米什  骑马去爱丁堡  召集贵族
Hamish, ride ahead to Edinburgh and assemble the council.
-命令他们开会  -好
- Order it. - Aye.
-你的岛  -我的岛  没错
- Your island? - My island! Yup!
你想谈判
You want to negotiate?
不  拜托  先生们
No, please, gentlemen!
领主们  克雷格说得对
Lords, Craig is right!
当下  我们唯一的选择就是谈判
This time, our only option is to negotiate.
除非你们想看着爱丁堡被夷为平地
Now, unless you want to see Edinburgh razed to the ground...
我的军队已经马不停蹄地行军不知道多少天了
My army has marched for more days than I can remember
我们还有准备要做
and we still have preparations to make,
所以我就直说了
so I'll make this plain.
我们需要你们能召集的所有士兵
We require every soldier you can summon.
你们的贴身侍卫  甚至你们自己
Your personal escorts, even yourselves,
现在就要
and we need them now.
现在大敌当前
With such a force arrayed against us,
是时候讨论其他方案了
it's time to discuss other options.
其他方案
Other options?
你们难道不希望至少带着你们的人到战场上去
Don't you wish at least to lead your men onto the field
跟长腿谈个更好的条件
and barter a better deal with Longshanks
然后再夹起尾巴逃跑吗
before you tuck tail and run?
-威廉爵士  -我们打不赢他们
- Sir William... - We can't defeat this army!
-我们能  -威廉爵士
- We can! - Sir William!
我们也会打赢
And we will!
我们在斯特灵取得了胜利  你们不置可否
We won at Stirling, and still you quibble!
我们在约克郡取得了胜利  你们还不愿支持我们
We won at York, and you would not support us.
如果你们现在不和我们并肩作战
If you'll not stand up with us now,
那要我说你们就是懦夫
then I say you're cowards.
你们要算是苏格兰人  我真是羞于与你们为伍
And if you are Scotsmen, I'm ashamed to call myself one.
威廉爵士  请单独和我聊聊
Please, Sir William, speak with me alone.
我请求你
I beg you.
你取得了任何人都不敢想象的胜利
Now, you've achieved more than anyone ever dreamed,
但这种形式下主战更像愤怒而非勇气
but fighting these odds, it looks like rage, not courage.
远不止是愤怒
It's well beyond rage.
帮帮我
Help me.
看在上帝的份上  帮帮你自己
In the name of Christ, help yourselves!
现在我们的机会来了  现在
Now is our chance. Now.
如果我们联合  我们就能赢
If we join, we can win.
我们赢了  就会取得
If we win, well, then we'll
前所未有的成就
have what none of us have ever had before.
我们自己的国家
A country of our own.
你是合法的领袖
You're the rightful leader,
我看见了你身上的力量
and there is strength in you. I see it.
团结我们
Unite us.
Unite us!
团结各族
Unite the clans.
好吧
All right.
好
Right.
不能这样
This cannot be the way.
你自己说的  贵族们不会支持华莱士
You said yourself, the nobles will not support Wallace.
加入被屠杀的一方  对我们有什么用
So how does it help us to join the side that is slaughtered?
我向他保证过了
I gave him my word.
我知道这很难
I know it is hard.
当领袖是很难
Being a leader is.
孩子...
Now, Son...
孩子  看着我
son, look at me.
我不能成为国王
I cannot be king.
只有你可以统治苏格兰
You and you alone can rule Scotland.
我告诉你的  你必须照做
What I tell you, you must do.
不是为我  也不是为你自己
Not for me, not for yourself,
而是为了你的国家
for your country.
福尔柯克
伙计  借过
Lads, make way.
让我们过去
Coming through you.
借过  伙计
Make way, lads.
借过...
Make...
布鲁斯不来了  威廉
The Bruce is not coming, William.
他会来的
He'll come.
莫尔奈和洛克林都来了
Mornay and Lochlan have come,
布鲁斯也会的
so will the Bruce.
好一次聚会
Quite a lovely gathering.
你觉得呢
Wouldn't you agree?
弓箭手已做好准备  陛下
The archers are ready, sire.
先不派弓箭手
Not the archers.
侦察兵告诉我  他们的弓箭手在几英里外呢
My scouts tell me their archers are miles away
对我们构不成威胁
and no threat to us.
箭很费钱  先打光爱尔兰人  死人不费钱
Arrows cost money. Use up the Irish. The dead cost nothing.
先派步兵和重骑兵
And send in the infantry and cavalry.
步兵
Infantry!
-步兵  -步兵
- Infantry! - Infantry!
重骑兵
Cavalry!
-重骑兵  -重骑兵
- Cavalry! - Cavalry!
前进
Advance!
-前进  -前进
- Advance! - Advance!
-今早见到你真高兴  -你好吗
- Good to see you this morning! - Hi. How are you?
爱尔兰人
Irish.
你和我们并肩作战真好
Glad to have you with us.
看好了
Watch this.
莫尔奈  洛克林
Mornay? Lochlan?
我让莫尔奈在苏格兰的土地翻了一倍
I gave Mornay double his lands in Scotland
还匹配了英格兰的领地给他
with matching estates in England.
洛克林要的可少得多
Lochlan turned for much less.
弓箭手
Archers.
您说什么  陛下
I beg pardon, sire.
这样不会伤到自己人吗
Won't we hit our own troops?
会
Yes,
但也会伤到他们
but we'll hit theirs as well.
我们还有后备军
We have reserves.
进攻
Attack.
弓箭手
Archers!
-弓箭手  -弓箭手
- Archers. - Archers.
放箭
Loose!
派出后续部队
Send in our reinforcements.
派出剩余军队
Send in the rest!
给我把华莱士抓来
Bring me Wallace.
尽可能活捉
Alive, if possible.
死了也可以
Dead, just as good.
把胜利的消息传给我们
Send us news of our victory.
我们可以撤了吧
Shall we retire?
保护国王
Protect the king.
起来
Get up!
快起来
起来
Up!
Get up!
-把他带走  -天啊
- Get him out of here! - Jesus!
快走
Go!
我快死了
I'm dying.
别管我了
Let me be.
不行
No.
你会活下来的
You're going to live.
我已经自由地活了够久了
I've lived long enough to live free.
看到你变成了这样的人  我很骄傲
Proud to see you become the man you are.
我是个幸福的人
I'm a happy man.
我是要入土的人
I'm the one who's rotting,
但你的脸色比我更死气沉沉
but I think your face looks graver than mine.
孩子
Son,
我们必须和英格兰结盟才能取得这里的胜利
we must have alliance with England to prevail here.
你做到了
You achieved that.
你拯救了家族也增加了领地
You saved your family, increased your land.
总有一天  你会掌握苏格兰的大权
In time, you will have all the power in Scotland.
领地  封号  人民  权力  我都没有
Lands, titles, men, power, nothing.
-都没有  -我一无所有
- Nothing? - I have nothing.
人民为我而战
Men fight for me
因为如果他们不照做  我就把他们
because if they do not, I throw them off my land
从我的领地上赶走  让他们的妻儿饿死
and I starve their wives and their children.
那些在福尔柯克血战的人
Those men who bled the ground red at Falkirk,
他们为威廉·华莱士而战
they fought for William Wallace,
他为某些我从未有过的东西而奋战
and he fights for something that I've never had.
我背叛了他  将那种东西夺走了
And I took it from him when I betrayed him,
战场上  我从他的脸上看出来了
and l saw it in his face on the battlefield,
这让我痛彻心扉
and it's tearing me apart!
是人都会背叛  都会失去本心
All men betray, all lose heart.
我不想失去本心
I don't want to lose heart!
我想像他一样坚信
I want to believe, as he does.
我再也不会做出错误的选择了
I will never be on the wrong side again.
不要  求求你
No, please!
他在这儿  快追
There he is! After him!
克雷格大人  莫尔奈的事是真的吗
Lord Craig, is it true about Mornay?
是真的
Aye.
华莱士骑着马进了他的卧室杀了他
Wallace rode into his bedchamber and killed him.
他现在比以前更碍事了
More a liability now than ever he was.
谁也不知道下一个会是谁
And there's no telling who'll be next.
也许是你
Maybe you.
也许是我
Maybe me.
无所谓了
It doesn't matter.
-我是认真的  罗伯特  -我也是
- I'm serious, Robert. - So am I!
老天啊  操
Christ! Shit!
给我搜
Search the place!
洛克林
Lochlan.
威廉·华莱士杀了五十个人
William Wallace killed 50 men.
轻而易举
Fifty if it was one.
他举剑杀了一百人
A hundred men with his own sword.
一剑劈死就像
Cut through them like...
就像穿越红海的摩西
Moses through the Red Sea.
他的传奇故事越传越广  情况会比以往更糟
His legend grows. It will be worse than before.
他在每个苏格兰城镇召集志愿者
He rallies new volunteers in every Scottish town,
等他召集到足够的人数
and when he replenishes his numbers...
他们只是绵羊  不堪一击
They're sheep, mere sheep!
只要打倒领头人他们就溃不成军了
Easily dispersed if we strike the shepherd.
好了
Very well.
挑几个你手下最优秀的杀手开个会
Pick a flock of your finest assassins and set a meeting.
陛下  华莱士以能察觉埋伏而闻名
Milord, Wallace is renowned for his ability to smell an ambush.
如果汉密尔顿大人所言属实
If what Lord Hamilton tells me is correct,
他对我们未来的王后有好感  并信任她
he warmed to our future queen and would trust her.
我们就派她假意和解
So we'll dispatch her with the notion that she comes in peace.
大人  王妃可能会被绑架
Milord, the princess might be taken hostage
或命悬一线
or her life be put in jeopardy.
那我儿子会很伤心的
My son would be most distressed by that.
但要是她被杀死
But in truth, if she were to be killed,
法国国王就会是我们对抗苏格兰的有力盟友
we would soon find the king of France a useful ally against the Scots.
你看  作为国王
You see, as king,
在任何情况下都要找到对自己有利的一面
you must find the good in any situation.
确认是威廉·华莱士
It's William Wallace, sure.
他扔掉了剑
He's given up his sword.
做好准备
Be ready.
夫人
Milady,
我收到了你的消息
I received your message.
这是你第二次警告我前方的危险了
This is the second time you have warned me of danger.
为什么
Why?
下个月会有一批新的补给运向北方
There will be a new shipment of supplies coming north next month.
里面有食物和武器  他们不会
Foods and weapons. They won't...
别说了
No, stop.
为什么要帮我
Why do you help me?
为什么帮我
因为你现在看我的那种眼神
Because of the way you are looking at me now.
就在我们希望尽失之时
Just when we thought all hope was lost,
我们的贵族救星来了
our noble saviors have arrived.
摘掉兜帽
Off with their hoods.
威廉爵士  我们是来寻求谈判的
Sir William, we've come to seek a meeting.
有什么可谈的
Well, what's the point?
你们都宣誓效忠长腿
You've all sworn loyalty to Longshanks.
对骗子的誓言根本不作数
An oath to a liar is no oath at all.
我们的人都准备好向你效忠了
Every man of us is ready to swear loyalty to you.
那就让议会公开宣誓
So let the council swear publicly.
那做不到  有些人甚至不相信你还活着
We cannot. Some scarcely believe you're alive.
剩下的人害怕会和莫尔奈一样的下场
Others think you'll pay them Mornay's wages.
所以我们邀请你去爱丁堡
So we bid you to Edinburgh.
两天后与我们会面
Meet us two days from now.
宽恕我们  我们将团结在你的身后
Pledge us your pardon, and we'll unite behind you.
苏格兰也会成为一体
Scotland will be one.
-一体  你说的是我们和你们吧  -不
- One? You mean us and you. - No.
我说的是这个
l mean this.
这是罗伯特·布鲁斯的信物
It's the pledge of Robert the Bruce.
你明知这是个陷阱  跟他说啊
You do know it's a trap. Tell him.
我觉得如果布鲁斯想杀你
I think if the Bruce wanted to kill you,
他在福尔柯克就下手了
he'd have done it already at Falkirk.
-是啊  -我知道  我看见了
- Aye. - I know. I saw.
不提他  其他人呢
Leaving him aside, what about the others?
那帮阴险狡诈的混蛋
Nest of scheming bastards!
他们不可能达成一致
They couldn't even agree on the color of shite!
这是个陷阱  你瞎了吗
It's a trap. Are you blind?
看看我们
Look at us.
我们得试试  不能孤军奋战
We've got to try. We can't do this alone.
联合贵族是人民唯一的希望
Joining the nobles is the only hope for our people.
你知道要是不抓住这机会会怎么样吗
You know what happens if we don't take that chance?
怎么样
What?
什么也不会发生
Nothing.
我不想当烈士
I don't want to be a martyr.
我也不想  我想活着
Nor I. I want to live.
我想有个家  有孩子  平静的生活
I want a home and children and peace.
-是吗  -是的  我想
- Do you? - Aye, I do.
我向上帝祈求过
I've asked God for those things.
但没有自由  那些不可能实现
It's all for nothing if you don't have freedom.
-那只是个梦  威廉  -梦  那只是
- That's just a dream, William. - A dream? Just a...
那我们一直都在干什么
Then what have we been doing all this time?
我们已经活在了梦中
We've lived that dream.
你梦的不是自由  而是梅伦
Your dream isn't about freedom. It's about Murron.
你当英雄是因为你觉得她在天上看着你
You're doing this to be a hero 'cause you think she sees you.
我不是觉得她在看着我  她就是在看着我
I don't think she sees me. I know she does.
你爸爸也在看着你
And your father sees you, too.
上帝啊
Jesus.
起来  把手给我
Get up. Give us your hand.
我能和你一起去吗
Shall I come with you?
不行  我自己去
No. I'll go alone.
回头见
I'll see you after.
好
Right.
但愿能尽快再见
Sooner rather than later, I hope.
-他不会来的  -他会来
- He won't come. - He will.
我知道他会来
I know he will.
大人  他来了
Milord, he approaches!
不
No!
你别插手  罗伯特
Stay out of it, Robert!
你骗我  你骗我
You lied! You lied!
不能伤害布鲁斯  我们说好的
Bruce is not to be hurt! That's the arrangement!
父亲
Father!
你个腐朽的老东西
You rotting bastard!
为什么  为什么
Why? Why?
长腿要抓威廉
Longshanks required Wallace.
我们的贵族也是
So did our nobles.
这就是王冠的代价
That was the price of your crown.
去死吧
Die!
你去死吧
I want you to die!
很快  我就会死而你就会成为国王
Soon enough, I'll be dead and you'll be king.
我不要你的任何东西
I don't want anything from you.
你根本不是人
You're not a man!
你不是我父亲
And you're not my father.
你是我儿子  你一直都知道我的想法
You're my son, and you have always known my mind.
你蒙骗了我
You deceived me.
是你任由自己被蒙骗
You let yourself be deceived.
你心里其实一直都知道这里要发生什么
In your heart, you always knew what had to happen here.
你终于知道憎恨是什么滋味了
At last, you know what it means to hate.
现在你已经准备好成为国王了
Now you're ready to be a king.
我的憎恨会随你一起死去
My hate will die with you.
威廉·华莱士
William Wallace,
你被控犯有严重叛国罪
you stand in taint of high treason.
背叛了谁
Against whom?
背叛了你的国王
Against your king.
你有什么要辩解的吗
Have you anything to say?
我这辈子
Never in my whole life
从没宣誓效忠于他
did I swear allegiance to him.
即便如此  他也是你的国王
It matters not. He is your king.
认罪  你可以死得痛快一些
Confess, and you may receive a quick death.
不认罪  你必须在痛苦中净化罪孽
Deny, and you must be purified by pain.
你认罪吗
Do you confess?
那么明天便开始你的净化
Then on the morrow, you shall receive your purification.
-殿下  -我要见囚犯
- Your Highness. - I will see the prisoner.
国王有令任何人...
We've got orders from the king that nobody...
国王月内就会驾崩  他的儿子又羸弱不堪
The king will be dead in a month and his son is a weakling.
你觉得到时候治理国家的会是谁
Who do you think will rule this kingdom?
立刻开门
Now open this door.
殿下
Majesty.
来吧  贱人  站起来
Come on, filth. Up on your feet.
住手
Stop it!
出去
Leave me.
我让你出去
I said leave me!
夫人
Milady.
大人  我是来求你
Sir, I come to beg you
认罪并宣誓效忠国王
to confess all and swear allegiance to the king
他或许会手下留情
that he might show you mercy.
他会对我的国家手下留情吗
Will he show mercy to my country?
手下留情是让你死得痛快一些
Mercy is to die quickly,
或是囚禁在塔楼
perhaps even live in a tower.
谁知道以后会发生什么
In time, who knows what can happen
只要你能活着
if you can only live.
如果我宣誓效忠他
If l swear to him,
那我已经与死无异了
then all that I am is dead already.
你会死的  刑罚会很残忍
You will die. It will be awful.
人都会死
Every man dies.
却不见得都活过
Not every man really lives.
喝了这个
Drink this.
这会减轻你的痛苦
It will dull your pain.
不行  它会麻木我的心智  而我需要它们
No. It will numb my wits, and I must have them all.
如果我昏过去  或是哀嚎
For if I'm senseless, or if I wail,
那长腿就是打垮了我
then Longshanks will have broken me.
一想到你会受的折磨我就无法忍受
I can't bear the thought of your torture.
喝了它吧
Take it.
好吧
All right.
我来求您饶威廉·华莱士一命
I have come to beg for the life of William Wallace.
你还真是喜欢他啊
You're quite taken with him, aren't you?
我尊敬他
I respect him.
至少他是个值得尊重的敌人
At worst, he was a worthy enemy.
请您手下留情  伟大的王
Show mercy, O thou great king,
赢得人民的尊敬
and win the respect of your own people.
即使到现在  你也不会宽恕
Even now, you are incapable of mercy.
而你...
And you...
对你来说  这个词就和爱一样陌生
To you, that word is as unfamiliar as love.
在他还能说话的时候
Before he lost his powers of speech,
他说他唯一的慰藉就是
he told me his one comfort was
能活着知道华莱士的死讯
that he would live to know Wallace was dead.
你看
You see,
我们都会死
death comes to us all.
在你死前  你记住
But before it comes to you, know this.
你的血脉也会随你而去
Your blood dies with you.
我肚子里怀了别人的孩子
A child who is not of your line grows in my belly.
你儿子的王位不会长久  我发誓
Your son will not sit long on the throne, I swear it.
我很害怕
I'm so afraid.
请赐我善终的力量
Give me the strength to die well.
他来了
Here he comes!
下面就是叛国要付出的惨痛代价
Now behold the awful price of treason!
你现在要跪下
You will fall to your knees now,
向国王表明你的忠心
declare yourself the king's loyal subject
并乞求他的宽恕
and beg his mercy.
我便会手下留情
And you shall have it.
绑住他
Rope!
把他拉上去
Stretch him!
就这样  拉住
That's it! Stretch him!
丢人  真丢人
Shame! Shame!
舒服吗
Pleasant, yes?
跪起来
Rise to your knees,
亲吻我斗篷上的皇室纹章
kiss the royal emblem on my cloak,
我便赐你个痛快
and you will feel no more.
用刑
Rack him!
受够了吗
Enough?
这一切都可以立刻结束
It can all end right now.
平静
Peace.
说出来就好
Please, just say it.
喊出  宽恕
Cry out, "Mercy."
宽恕
Mercy!
宽恕  宽恕
Mercy! Mercy!
喊吧
Cry out.
宽恕  宽恕
Mercy! Mercy!
说吧
Just say it.
宽恕
Mercy.
宽恕  宽恕
Mercy! Mercy!
请求宽恕吧  威廉
Mercy, William.
-请求宽恕吧  -天啊  快说吧
- Mercy. - Jesus, now say it.
犯人想说句话
The prisoner wishes to say a word.
宽恕  宽恕
Mercy! Mercy!
宽恕
Mercy!
自由
Freedom!
被砍头之后
After the beheading,
威廉·华莱士的身体被五马分尸
William Wallace's body was torn to pieces.
他的头被挂在伦敦桥上
His head was set on London Bridge,
他的四肢被送往英国的四境
his arms and legs sent to the four corners of Britain
作为警告
as a warning.
但这并没有起到长腿期望的效果
It did not have the effect that Longshanks planned.
而我  罗伯特·布鲁斯
And I, Robert the Bruce,
亲自前来向英国国王的军队表示效忠
rode out to pay homage to the armies of the English king
并接受他对我王位的认可
and accept his endorsement of my crown.
希望你今早洗了屁股
I hope you've washed your arse this morning.
马上就要有国王亲它了
It's about to be kissed by a king.
走吧  赶紧完事
Come. Let's get it over with.
等等
Stop!
你们曾追随华莱士浴血奋战
You have bled with Wallace!
现在追随我吧
Now bleed with me.
华莱士  华莱士
Wallace! Wallace!
华莱士  华莱士  华莱士  华莱士
Wallace! Wallace! Wallace! Wallace!
公元1314年
In the year of our Lord, 1314,
苏格兰的爱国者们在缺衣少粮敌众我寡的情况下
patriots of Scotland, starving and outnumbered,
在班诺克本战场上发起进攻
charged the fields of Bannockburn.
他们像诗中的战士一样战斗
They fought like warrior poets.
像苏格兰人一样战斗
They fought like Scotsmen,
赢得了自由
and won their freedom.